# Charlotte J. Lambert

cjl8@illinois.edu · charlottelambert.github.io

## **Research Objective**

My research aims to make online spaces more welcoming to its users through the encouragement of healthy behaviors and improved methods of moderation. Broadly, my interests are at the intersection of Human-Computer Interaction and Natural Language Processing. Currently, my focus is on examining factors that contribute to healthy and unhealthy online conversations. Specifically, I am working on devising proactive methods to facilitate online conversations that are resilient to the influence of adverse behavior.

Keywords: Online communities, social computing, healthy behaviors, moderation

### **Education**

#### · University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Ph.D. in Computer Science

Urbana, IL 2020-present

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Research Interests: Social Computing, Natural Language Processing

• Vassar College
Bachelor of Arts in Computer Science, Minors in Mathematics and Italian; GPA: 3.9/4.0

Poughkeepsie, NY

2016-2020

- Thesis: Temporal Exploration of the Proceedings of Old Bailey
- Research Advisors: Jonathan Gordon and Jennifer Walter

#### **Publications**

• Conversational Resilience: Quantifying and Predicting Conversational Outcomes Following Adverse Events. In the 16th International Conference on Web and Social Media

Charlotte Lambert, Ananya Rajagopal, and Eshwar Chandrasekharan

• Inter-Sense: An Investigation of Sensory Blending in Fiction. In First International Workshop on Multisensory Data & Knowledge: The 3rd Conference on Language, Data and Knowledge (2021)

Corina R. Ğirju and Charlotte Lambert

- Conversation-Level Resilience. Poster in the First Workshop on NLP for Positive Impact: ACL-IJCNLP 2021 Charlotte Lambert and Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Story Immersion: Toward Fiction Synesthesia for Enhanced Reader Empathy. Presentation in Uncommon Senses Conference (2021)

Corina R. Girju and Charlotte Lambert

# Research Experience

Graduate Research Assistant

Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

Urbana, IL Fall 2021 - present

- Advisor: Eshwar Chandrasekharan
- Project: Conversation-Level Resilience to Bad Actors in Reddit Communities
- Area of Work: Human-Computer Interaction

Undergraduate Research Assistant

Department of Computer Science, Vassar College

Poughkeepsie, NY 2018-2020

- Advisor: Jonathan Gordon; Project: Computational Models of Literary Variation
- Assisted on projects related to natural language processing
- Analyzed patterns in data collected about the use of language in a corpus of books
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing

**Distributed Research Experiences for Undergraduates (DREU) Intern** *Department of Computer Science, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign* 

Urbana, IL Summer 2019

- Advisor: Julia Hockenmaier; Project: Collaborative Dialogue in Minecraft
- Started building fully interactive agents to communicate using natural language in a 3D environment
- Used concepts in NLP and deep learning to improve quality of utterances generated by two agents

- Worked on neural network to recognize shapes in 3D with nearly 100% accuracy
- Area of Work: Natural Language Processing, Machine Learning

### Research Experiences for Undergraduates (REU) Intern

University of Southern California Institute for Creative Technologies

Los Angeles, CA Summer 2018

- Advisor: Jonathan Gratch, Gale Lucas; Project: Impact of AI on User Psychology
- Developed and optimized code to support a system to be used to carry out a future study
- Worked to create realistic AI capable of negotiating online with users and other AIs
- Area of Work: Artificial Intelligence

## **Professional Experience**

Graduate Research Intern

San Francisco, CA

Summer 2022

Twitch Interactive, Mentor: Ruth Toner Worked on projects related to community health on the Twitch platform.

## Teaching Experience

**Intro Computing: Non-Tech (CS 105)** 

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Spring 2023, Fall 2023

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Colleen Lewis, Craig Zilles Lead lab sections; Assist in group-work during lecture; Hold weekly office hours.

Discrete Math (CS 173)

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Spring 2021, Summer 2021, Fall 2022

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Benjamin Cosman Guide weekly group discussions; Evaluate weekly exams; Hold weekly office hours.

**Introduction to Computer Science (CS 125)** 

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Teaching Assistant, Instructor: Dr. Geoffrey Challen

Fall 2020

Co-led an optional weekly recap of course material for between 50 and 100 undergraduates.

### Awards and Honors

•	Ranked as Excellent by Students, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign	Spring 2023
---	--	-------------

C.W. Gear Outstanding Graduate Student, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign Award given to one graduate student who has demonstrated excellence in research and service. 2023

**ICWSM 2022 Virtual Scholarship** 

2022

Scholarship awarded to virtual conference participants from underrepresented groups.

Saburo Muroga Endowed Fellowship, University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

2020-2021

*Fellowship awarded to outstanding graduate students in computer science.* 

**Graduated with Departmental Honors**, Vassar College Honors awarded to students nominated by the Computer Science Department for academic excellence. 2020

**Graduated with General Honors**, Vassar College

2020

Honors awarded to the top 20% of the graduating class.

2020

**Honorary Sigma Xi Nomination**, Vassar College

Awarded to graduating seniors nominated based upon their research accomplishments and academic record.

# **Professional Service and Volunteering**

Reviewer

Computer-Supported Cooperative Work (CSCW)

2023

Reviewer

International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media (ICWSM)

2022

Girls Who Code Co-Lead Facilitator

2021-2023

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

Sub-reviewer

"AAAI-MAKE: Combining Machine Learning and Knowledge Engineering Practice," AAAI Spring Symposium 2020, Stanford University

## Languages

Italian (proficient); Spanish (reading)

# **Programming**